A Guide to the Papers of The Center for Nursing Historical Inquiry 1934-2001
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
- CNHI: Kathryn Jaquette Papers 1969-1974, 3 boxes, 1.25 linear feet
  This collection consists of training program protocols, practice protocols, legislative materials, educational pamphlets, journal articles, and newspaper articles related to the nurse practitioner movement in the 1970s. The materials in the Jaquette Papers are the result of her research into NP protocols for the National Health Service, a task assigned by the Service with the intent to use the data to develop a standard NP protocol. After collecting information from NP public health programs around the country, however, the Service concluded that conditions of practice were so variable, and medical practice changed so rapidly, that the establishment of a uniform national NP protocol was not feasible. The papers reflect the state of NP practice in the United States in the 1970s, a period when the NP movement was just beginning and standards were being determined. The nurse practitioner now constitutes a recognized advanced practice nursing specialty, with established professional organizations, certification standards, and standards of practice. The Jaquette Papers help to shed light on the early development of this important nursing specialty.
  The collection has been arranged into one topical series, reflecting the order in which the material was originally organized.
  - Series 1: Expanded Role for Nurses
    - Expanded Role for Nurses (Box-folder 001-001)
      Re: Doctors and nurses: changing roles and relations; The primary care nurse; Questionnaire on selected professional activities of the FNP; The nature of nursing tomorrow.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-002)
      Re: Family doctors' use of office assistants and opinions; Doctor-patient communication; Not quite MD, more than PA; The two languages of nursing and medicine; Who will provide more health care? Nurse and physician's assistant: issues and relationships.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-003)
      Re: A year in Mayo: The Lafayette County Health Center; Lafayette County Health report for 1970; NLN news: nurses in expanded roles; Situation for Martin County population in Appalachia, Kentucky.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-004)
      Re: Curriculum for nurse practitioners; Suggested reading list: expanded role of nurses; ANA: nurses, in the expanded role, are not physician's assistants; The nursing practice act of New York State; Nurse's role in clinical practice; Expanded Duty Program.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-005)
      Re: The nurse's role; Expanded role article list (Volume I and II); 1973 Primex internship class content; MD assistants course to continue in 1975; The medical educational environment; Georgia loses a nurse in medical dispute; Suggested reading list for expanded role of nurses; New health professionals at Kaiser; A question of role ambiguity.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-006)
      Re: Primex family nurse practitioner program; Primex core objectives for educational program.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-007)
      Re: Primex family nurse practitioner program calendar, NHSC utilization of nurse.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-008)
      Re: Suggested reading list of expanded role of nurse; Working definition of family nurse practitioner; Doctor and nurse: changing roles and relations.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-009)
      Re: The new standing orders and their pitfalls; Legal material regarding nurse practitioners; Rules of composite state board of medical examiners-physician assistant.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-010)
      Re: State legislation for physician's assistants-a review and analysis; Special article on the training of physician assistants.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-011)
      Re: Abstracts of articles related to nurse practitioner clinics; Let's get the nurse's role into focus; A health maintenance service for chronically ill patients; Guidelines for prospective reimbursement experiments and demonstration projects under the Medicare, Medicaid, and maternal child health program.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-012)
      Re: Laying the foundation for medical nursing practice; The legal bases for nursing practice; Certification of school nurses Jaquette, cont'd.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-013)
      Re: Seeking a co-equal status for nurses and physicians; ANA convention journal.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-015)
      Re: Thanks to Martha Schwebach; Two nurses open Suffolk Clinic to give primary health care; Fund drive for Saluda Medical Center is officially underway.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-015)
      Re: ANA convention journal; Newspaper articles related to nurse practitioners and physician assistants.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-016)
      Re: Selected geographic locations in which extended roles of the nurse are now being demonstrated; Program for nurse clinician; ANA scope of practice for pediatric nurse practitioner.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-017)
      Re: A community wants a family nurse clinician; Experience of a nurse practitioner in a general medical clinic; Madison health access station.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-018)
      Re: The expanded role of the nurse at the Atlanta Southside Comprehensive Health Center; Procedural Suggestions for State Nurses Associations in supporting the nurse practitioner in the area of dependent nursing function; The relative roles of the public health nurse and the physician in prenatal and infant supervision.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-019)
      Re: A report of the Secretary's Committee to study extended roles for nurses; Nursing Outlook regarding the nurse practitioner.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-020)
      Re: Federal nursing service award; miscellaneous hand written documents.
  - Series 2: Nurse Practitioner Primary Care Guide and Protocols
    - Nurse Practitioner Primary Care Guide and Protocols (Box-folder 002-001)
      Re: Standing orders for the use of the health team of United Health Services of Kentucky and Tennessee.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 002-002)
      Re: Primary care guide for hypertension, diabetes.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 002-003)
      Re: Primary care guide for diabetes and skin complication.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 002-004)
      Re: Medical standing orders for Itinerant public health nurses.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 002-005)
      Re: Maternal and Infant care and communicable disease management.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 002-006)
      Re: Acute and chronic conditions management.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 002-007)
      Re: General medical and legal management and recommended prescriptions.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 002-008)
      Re: The nurse clinician's workbook (Part I).
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 002-009)
      Re: The nurse clinician's workbook (Part II).
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 002-010)
      Re: Pediatric care from State University of IOWA department of Pediatrics.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 002-011)
      Re: Criteria and techniques for diagnosis of gonorrhea, treatment for skin problems.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 002-012)
      Re: Coronary artery disease treatment.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 002-013)
      Re: Nutrition clinic: Recipes for Diabetic Diet.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 002-014)
      Re: Standing orders for pediatric care.
    - (Box-folder 002-015)
      Re: Nurse practitioner standing orders for adult medical patients.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 002-016)
      Re: Obstetrics in general practice; Standing orders for Pediatric Nurse Associate.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 002-017)
      Re: Protocols for paramedics; data base.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 002-018)
      Re: Pediatric screening for nurse practitioner; Instruction for medications.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 002-019)
      Re:
  - Series 3: Training Programs and Job Description Materials: Materials Related to Legislation
    - NP Training Program, Job Description, and Legislation (Box-folder 003-001)
      Re: General nurse practitioner training programs throughout U.S.; FNP program experience log; Nurse clinician job description.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-002)
      Re: Job descriptions for nurse practitioners.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-003)
      Re: Nurse practitioner-job description.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-004)
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-005)
      Re: Proposed rules and regulations for certified nurse practitioners.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-006)
      Re: A directory of program training: physician support training; The emerging physician's assistant.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-007)
      Re: A survey of health care functions and responsibilities of physician's assistants.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-008)
      Re: Practice profiles; Community relations activities.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-009)
      Re: Staff protocols.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-010)
      Re: Examples for financial, medical record, registration.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-011)
      Re: Miscellaneous.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-012)
      Re: Lincoln Hospital house-staff medical manual.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-013)
      Re: Essentials of the neurological examination; Commonly encountered neurologic disorders.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-014)
      Re: Revision of standing orders for registered nurse practitioners; miscellaneous treatment protocol.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-015)
      Re: Standing orders for diabetes; miscellaneous treatment protocols.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-016)
      Re: Hope Medical Center adult and child chart.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-017)
      Re: Basic treatment guidelines for nurse practitioners.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-018)
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-019)
      Re: Medical directives for the use of the nursing staff of the Frontier Nursing Service.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 003-020)
      Re: Nurse administered units; Final report for a new manpower model of rural-urban linkage for improved health services.
- CNHI: Louise Paris Jones Papers 1946-1998, 4 boxes, 2.0 linear feet
  The collection consists primarily of publications, presentations, memos, professional notes, journal articles, and correspondence related to Mrs. Jones' work as a psychiatric mental health certified nurse specialist and as a licensed counselor. The materials date from the 1940s to the 1990s, and represent an overview of Jones' varied career as clinician, counselor, instructor, administrator, and consultant; documenting her education, professional roles and activities, and continuing education.
  The collection has been arranged into five series, reflecting topical and functional divisions imposed by Jones. These are: educational materials, graduate records, research papers, nursing history, and work records. To conserve space, only the first pages of journal articles have been retained.
  - Series 1: Educational Materials 1946 - 1998
    - Anger 1970 - 1990 (Box-folder 001-001)
      Re: Journal articles, cartoons, presentation notes, and anger worksheets.
    - Anxiety 1973 - 1993 (Box-folder 001-002)
      Re: Journal articles, book chapter, NIH treatment guidelines, educational booklet.
    - Borderline Personality Disorder 1975 - 1994 (Box-folder 001-003)
      Re: Journal articles, emails, and papers.
    - Communication 1971 - 1986 (Box-folder 001-004)
      Re: Journal articles, cartoons, presentation notes; guidelines on communication, listening, family communication, public speaking.
    - Competency Model 1973 - 1975 (Box-folder 001-005)
      Re: "Competency Model" lecture, evaluation tool, continuing education papers and audiovisual handout originals.
    - Coronary Care 1972 (Box-folder 001-006)
      Re: Materials for coronary care nursing course include agenda, lectures, and EKG samples.
    - Critical Care 1974 - 1975 (Box-folder 001-007)
      Re: Materials for "Critical Care" nursing course including agenda, quizzes, and anatomical drawings.
    - Depressive Disorders 1977 - 1992 (Box-folder 001-008)
      Re: NIH guidelines on depression in late life, book chapter copy, US Dept. of Health & Human Services booklets on depression in primary care, notes on teleconference.
    - Defense Mechanisms 1970 - 1995 (Box-folder 001-009)
      Re: Cartoons depicting defense mechanisms, definitions of defense mechanisms.
    - Educational Materials: Eating Disorders 1990s (Box-folder 001-010)
      Re: Materials on "Eating Feelings" seminar, handouts on eating-related topics, eating habits questionnaire.
    - Emergency Psychiatric Care 1960 - 1994 (Box-folder 001-011)
      Re: Lecture materials from file titled "Understanding the Psychiatric Patient," Attitude Inventory Exercise, guidelines for managing psychiatric emergencies, brochure for emergency service.
    - Groups 1947 - 1979 (Box-folder 001-012)
      Re: Articles, nurse-specific group information, team development guidebook, booklets on developing work relationships and getting acquainted, guides to human relations theories, group roles.
    - Groups - Continued 1980 - 1992 (Box-folder 001-013)
      Re: Journal articles, leadership packet for "Surviving Dysfunctional Families", problem-solving materials, bibliography.
    - Groups - Continued 1993 - 1996 (Box-folder 002-001)
      Re: Group skills, protocol, outcomes, leadership styles, objectives, and roles, group workshop papers, pyscho-educational group rating Scale.
    - Groups - Continued [n.d.] (Box-folder 002-002)
      Re: Group Process class originals, ethical guidelines for group leaders, Johari window, family interview, Stress exercises, handling group conflict, group methods.
    - Mental Health 1974 - 1997 (Box-folder 002-003)
      Re: Social competency paper; articles and guides on parenting and child custody, specific emotions, assumptions of mental health, feelings.
    - Psychiatric Assessment & Treatment 1973 - 1989 (Box-folder 002-004)
      Re: Mental status manual, outline for psychiatric examination, AIMS Scale, mini-mental state examination, psychosexual-social history questionnaire and timeline, client information form for Mental Health Services of Roanoke Valley, inservice notes.
    - Psych. Asesssment & Treatment - Cont. 1990 - 1995 (Box-folder 002-005)
      Re: Admission database, role-play, "Metaphor: A Bridge to the Unconscious" presentation, assessment guidelines, articles, and client contact sheet.
    - Psychiatric Disorders/Mental Illness 1966 - 1998 (Box-folder 002-006)
      Re: Journal articles, UVA patient care plans, materials on counseling principles and ego states, letter concerning a client's diagnosis.
    - Scales and Testing Materials 1980 - 1989 (Box-folder 002-007)
      Re: Patient worksheet originals.
    - Scales & Testing Materials - Cont. 1989 - 1996 (Box-folder 002-008)
      Re: MMPI evaluation, patient questionnaires, patient worksheet originals, social position index, geriatric depression scale, feelings inventory.
    - Self-Esteem 1962 - 1976 (Box-folder 002-009)
      Re: Journal articles, introduction to self-concept, handwritten notes.
    - Self-Esteem - Continued 1977 - 1994 (Box-folder 002-010)
      Re: Literature review, articles on self-esteem, patient worksheet originals.
    - Self-Esteem Group 1995 (Box-folder 002-011)
      Re: Handwritten and typed notes, self-esteem group protocol, and group therapy packet which includes theory, strategies, and exercises.
    - The Role of the Psychiatric Nurse 1974 - 1992 (Box-folder 002-012)
      Re: Letters, notes, copy of speech and other documents related to a lecture given by Jones.
    - Therapeutic Milieu 1946 - 1993 (Box-folder 002-013)
      Re: List of basic assumptions of human behavior, material for client education, inpatient rules and guidelines.
  - Series 2: Graduate Records 1972 - 1979
    - Graduate School Records 1972 - 1977 (Box-folder 002-014)
      Re: Course outlines and syllabi.
    - Graduate School Records - Cont. 1976 - 1977 (Box-folder 002-015)
      Re: Papers written by Jones for graduate coursework: Anger: Color it Red; Personal Reaction Paper/Learning Papers; Analysis of Organizational Problem; Intellectualization as a Coping Behavior in Manic- Depressive Psychosis; Problem Paper.
    - Graduate School Records - Cont. 1976 - 1979 (Box-folder 002-016)
      Re: Course syllabi.
  - Series 3: Research Papers 1973 - 1997
    - Research Papers 1973 - 1978 (Box-folder 003-001)
      Re: Tracheostomy study and patient classification study by Jones.
    - Research Papers - Continued 1978-1981 (Box-folder 003-002)
      Re: Documents related to Jones' masters thesis, Tennessee Self-Concept Scale, case study report, and documents related to study to evaluate effects of exercise on diabetic rats.
    - Research Papers - Continued 1993 - 1997 (Box-folder 003-003)
      Re: Documents related to Virginia Twin Project.
  - Series 4: Nursing History 1911 - 1992
    - Nursing History 1911 - 1984 (Box-folder 003-004)
      Re: Letters and papers regarding the history of the Nightingale Pledge, nursing cap history, student nurses association newsletter, AAHN Conference booklet, and the International Council of Nurses.
    - Nursing History - Continued 1937 - 1985 (Box-folder 003-005)
      Re:Sarah Luster's History of Roanoke Memorial Hospital, including related correspondence and photocopies of original documents such as a Cadet Nurse Certificate.
  - Series 5: Work Records 1971 - 1998
    - Work Records 1971 - 1976 (Box-folder 003-006)
      Re: Handbook "Everything You Always Wanted to Know About Nursing Service in 1971", patient bill of rights pamphlet, ANA newsletter, VNA letter.
    - Work Records - Continued 1976 (Box-folder 003-007)
      Re: Copy of Vocational-Technical Education Consortium of States catalog on nursing assistance occupations, including letter thanking Jones for her contributions to its creation.
    - Work Records - Continued 1976 - 1980 (Box-folder 003-008)
      Re: Reports by Jones on St. Albans Psychiatric Hospital, where she served as director of clinical nursing; inservice education papers and brochures.
    - Work Records - Continued 1978 - 1980 (Box-folder 003-009)
      Re: Correspondence related to Jones' counseling practice, her job description, and legal, informational materials on licensed professional counselors.
    - Work Records - Continued 1980 - 1982 (Box-folder 003-010)
      Re: Documents from Jones' role as director of Emergency Outreach Services in Roanoke; client contact form, job evaluation forms, correspondence related to patients and personnel.
    - Work Records - Continued 1982 - 1986 (Box-folder 003-011)
      Re: Documents from Jones' role as director of Roanoke Memorial Hospital (RMH) School of Nursing, including psychiatric nursing standards, sample of counseling work, report on the status of the school, and correspondence related to the functioning of the school and to Jones' counseling licensure and practice.
    - Work Records - Continued 1985 (Box-folder 003-012)
      Re: RMH School of Nursing documents: SON catalogue, personnel evaluation forms, notes for banding ceremony, annual report, and correspondence related to development of a BSN program.
    - Work Records - Continued 1985 (Box-folder 003-013)
      Re: RMH School of Nursing documents: Student handbook, test performance report.
    - Work Records - Continued 1986 (Box-folder 004-001)
      Re: RMH School of Nursing documents: Faculty development survey, proposal to join forces with Ferrum College for a BSN program, performance evaluation documents, NLN test results, and faculty minutes.
    - Work Records - Continued 1988 (Box-folder 004-002)
      Re: RMH School of Nursing documents: clinical skills performance checklist, school logo, school philosophy, definition of organizations.
    - Work Records - Continued 1992 - 1993 (Box-folder 004-003)
      Re: Documents related to Jones' employment as a psychiatric clinical nurse specialist at the Salem, Virginia Veteran's Affairs Medical Center (VAMC). This includes job application, job descriptions, performance evaluations, and correspondence.
    - Work Records - Continued 1994 (Box-folder 004-004)
      Re: Salem VAMC documents: includes performance evaluations, materials related to workshops and programs conducted by Jones, documents related to expert legal testimony by Jones.
    - Work Records - Continued 1995 (Box-folder 004-005)
      Re: Salem VAMC documents: includes performance evaluations, materials related to workshops and programs conducted by Jones, job descriptions, discussion of client issues.
    - Work Records - Continued 1995-1996 (Box-folder 004-006)
      Re: Salem VAMC: Materials on the role and definition of the clinical nurse specialist; correspondence about therapy groups and courses/workshops taught by Jones, and concerning Jones' resignation; Jones' ideas for improving function of her unit of VAMC; personnel records and evaluations.
    - Work Records - Continued 1997 (Box-folder 004-007)
      Re: Licensing and re-certification documents, and Center for Emotional Wellness employment agreement.
    - Work Records: Continuing Education 1980 - 1998 (Box-folder 004-008)
      Re: Notes, handouts, correspondence, and certificates from continuing education sessions attended.
    - Work Records: Equal Employment Opportunity 1995 (Box-folder 004-009)
      Re: Documents from EEO training course and from specific cases handled by Jones.
    - Work Records: Groups 1993 - 1995 (Box-folder 004-010)
      Re: Documents removed from a binder labeled: "Therapeutic Program-Building 8", relating to Jones' work as a group facilitator for the psychiatric unit at the Salem VAMC. Includes protocols for groups, scheduling, etc.
    - Work Records: Client Papers 1992 - 1995 (Box-folder 004-011)
      Re: Correspondence from client-related court case. Handwritten notes (charting) and associated correspondence from therapy group for female veterans.
    - Client Papers- Continued 1993 - 1995 (Box-folder 004-012)
      Re: Protocol for psychoeducational groups, handwritten notes from interpersonal group.
    - Work Records: Anger Group 1993 - 1994 (Box-folder 004-013)
      Re: Book I - Handwritten notes (charting) from anger group.
    - Work Records: Anger Group - Continued 1994 - 1996 (Box-folder 004-014)
      Re: Book II - Handwritten notes (charting) from anger group.
- CNHI: The Gloria K. Nuckles Papers 1950-1953, 1 box, .4 linear feet
  The papers of Gloria (Rhinesmith) Nuckles include class notes, quizzes and exams from 1950-54, as well as notes taken during her psychiatric nursing training at Eastern State Hospital in Williamsburg (1953).
  - Series 1: Nursing Coursework
    - Rules of Nursing Care 1950 (Box-folder 001-001)
      Re: Riverside Hospital, Newport News, Va, typed procedures.
    - Nursing History 1950 (Box-folder 001-002)
      Re: Classroom notes & tests.